<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Java date and time API - Home</title>
  <author email="scolebourne@users.sourceforge.net">Stephen Colebourne</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

<section name="Joda Time - Java date and time API">

<p>
Joda-Time aims to provide a quality replacement for the Java <i>date</i> and <i>time</i> classes.
The design allows for multiple <i>calendar</i> systems, while still providing simple API.
The 'default' calendar is the <a href="cal_iso.html">ISO8601</a> standard which is used by XML.
The Gregorian, Julian, Buddhist and Coptic systems are also included, and we welcome further additions.
Supporting classes include time zone, duration, format and parsing.
</p>

<p>
The decision to create a cleanroom date implementation to replace Java's is based on the flaws in the JDK code.
Date should have been immutable, like String, instead it is mutable and has many deprecated methods.
Calendar makes accessing 'normal' dates difficult, due to the lack of simple methods.
It also has some strange performance characteristics as it recalculates fields at unexpected moments.
</p>

<p>
Using a Joda date you can write:
</p>
<source>
DateTime dt = new DateTime();
int year = dt.getYear();
String monthText = dt.monthOfYear().getAsText(Locale.ENGLISH);
String monthInFrench = dt.monthOfYear().getAsText(Locale.FRENCH);
String dateAsISO8601Format = dt.toString();
</source>
<p>
And this is only a flavour of what is available, see the <a href="api-0.95/index.html">API</a>
or <a href="userguide.html">users guide</a> for more detail.
</p>

<p>
Current interfaces and implementations include:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Instant</li>
<li>DateTime</li>
<li>DateMidnight</li>
<li>YearMonthDay</li>
<li>TimeOfDay</li>
<li>Duration</li>
<li>Period</li>
<li>Interval</li>
<li>Chronology</li>
<li>DateTimeZone</li>
<li>...plus formatting and parsing</li>
</ul>

<p>
Joda Time is licenced under the <a href="license.html">Joda licence</a>,
which is an Apache/BSD cloned licence.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Documentation">
<p>
Various documentation is available:
</p>
<ul>
<li>The <a href="userguide.html">user guide</a></li>
<li>The key concepts and chronology documents in the left navigation area</li>
<li>The javadoc for the <a href="api-0.95/index.html">current release</a></li>
<li>The javadoc for the <a href="apidocs/index.html">latest CVS</a></li>
<li>A <a href="faq.html">FAQ</a> list</li>
<li>The <a href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/joda-time/JodaTime">CVS repository</a></li>
</ul>

</section>

<section name="Releases">
<p>
<a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=97367&amp;package_id=104212&amp;release_id=217327">Release 0.95</a>
is the current latest release.
This release is stable in that it tells the right time, and we are aware of sites where it has been used in production.
However, there have been significant API changes to the CVS version since 0.95, all resulting from issues identified in testing.
It is hoped to release a new release in Q4 2004.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Support">
<p>
For support on bugs, using the library or to volunteer please contact the <a href="mail-lists.html">mailing list</a>
(or email direct to the list via <a href="mailto:joda-interest@lists.sourceforge.net">joda-interest@lists.sourceforge.net</a>).
</p>
<p>
Alternatively, you can contact the project lead, Stephen Colebourne via
<a href="mailto:scolebourne@users.sourceforge.net">scolebourne@users.sourceforge.net</a>.
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
