<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>Joda Time</title>
  <author email="scolebourne@users.sourceforge.net">Stephen Colebourne</author>
 </properties>

 <body>

<section name="Joda Time">

<p>
<b>Joda-Time is an open-source project to provide a quality Java date and time API.</b>
</p>

<p>
Date and Time handling is fundamental to many applications.
However, the classes supplied in Java have always been weak.
Date should have been immutable, like String.
Instead, it has many deprecated methods.
Calendar makes accessing 'normal' dates difficult, due to the lack of simple methods.
Calendar also has some strange performance characteristics. 
</p>

<p>
The Joda Dates project seeks to provide an implementation of dates and times for the Java community.
The 'default' calendar system implemented will be the ISO8601 standard.
This specifies a framework for date and time independent of locale.
Thus, in the standard, the first day of the week is Monday, and this has the index 1.
This avoids any ambiguity accross national boundaries.
</p>

<p>
Additional calendar systems supported are Gregorian, Julian, GregorianJulian (GJ) and Buddhist.
The design is flexible and pluggable, so adding additional calendar systems should be easy. 
</p>

<p>
Using a Joda date you can write:
</p>
<source>
DateTime dt = new DateTime();
int year = dt.getYear();
String monthText = dt.monthOfYear().getAsText(Locale.ENGLISH);
String monthInFrench = dt.monthOfYear().getAsText(Locale.FRENCH);
String dateAsISO8601Format = dt.toString();
</source>
<p>
And this is only a flavour of what is available, see the <a href="api-0.9/index.html">API</a>
or <a href="userguide.html">users guide</a> for more detail.
</p>

<p>
Current interfaces and implementations include:
</p>
<ul>
<li>Instant</li>
<li>DateTime</li>
<li>DateOnly</li>
<li>TimeOnly</li>
<li>Duration</li>
<li>DateTimeZone</li>
<li>...plus formatting and parsing</li>
</ul>

<p>
Joda Time is licenced under the <a href="license.html">Joda licence</a>,
which is an Apache/BSD cloned licence.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Documentation">
<p>
The JavaDoc API documents are available online for the
<a href="api-0.9/index.html">current release</a> and the
<a href="apidocs/index.html">latest CVS</a>.
</p>
<p>
The <a href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/viewcvs.py/joda-time">CVS repository</a> can be browsed.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Releases">
<p>
<a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=97367&amp;package_id=104212">Release 0.9</a>
is the current latest release. It is reasonably stable, although some APIs will change for 1.0.
</p>
</section>

<section name="Contact">
<p>
If you have any questions, or want to volunteer to help, just email
<a href="mailto:scolebourne@users.sourceforge.net">scolebourne@users.sourceforge.net</a>
</p>
</section>
</body>
</document>
