<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>

<document>
 <properties>
  <title>Java date and time API - Upgrade from 1.5 to 1.6</title>
  <author>Stephen Colebourne</author>
 </properties>

<body>

<section name="Upgrade">
<p>
These are the release notes and advice for upgrading Joda-Time from
version 1.5 to version 1.6.
<source>
Joda-Time version 1.6
---------------------

Joda-Time is a date and time handling library that seeks to replace the JDK
Date and Calendar classes.

This is the seventh release of Joda-Time.
This release contains enhancements, bug fixes and a time zone update.

We recommend JDK 1.4 or later, and have performed no testing on earlier JDKs.

Joda-Time is licensed under the business-friendly Apache License Version 2.
This is the same license as all of Apache, plus other open source projects such as Spring.
The intent is to make the code available to the Java community with the minimum
of restrictions. If the license causes you problems please contact the mailing list.

**  Please also check out our related projects   **
** http://joda-time.sourceforge.net/related.html **

********************************************************************
 The next release will probably be v2.0
 This will be source and binary compatible with the exception that
 deprecated methods and classes will be removed.
 If you rely on the deprecated methods or classes please move to
 their replacements, or let us know why you can't move by writing
 in https://sourceforge.net/forum/forum.php?forum_id=337835
********************************************************************


Enhancements since 1.5
----------------------
- Add static factory methods to Duration [1909376]
  Duration now has four factory methods, standardDays(), standardHours(),
  standardMinutes() and standardSeconds(). These create durations of the
  length normally associated with a day/hour/minute/second

- Added Duration.getStandardSeconds() and Duration.toStandardSeconds()
  These convert a duration in milliseconds to a number of seconds.

- Added OSGi bundle information [1889787]
  Joda-Time should be usable directly as an OSGi bundle

- Added stable Chronology hash code implementations [2018795]
  The hash codes of each Chronology implementation is now stable.
  This should aid large scale caching/distribution tools.

- Added DateTimeZone.isLocalDateTimeGap
  Returns true/false depending on whether the time is in a time-zone gap


Compatibility with 1.5
----------------------
Binary compatible - Yes

Source compatible - Yes

Serialization compatible - Yes

Data compatible - Yes, except
  - DateTimeZone data updated to version 2008i

Semantic compatible - Yes


Deprecations since 1.5
----------------------


Bug fixes since 1.5
-------------------
- ISODateTimeFormat millisecond parsing broken
  Millisecond parsing would parse 12:00:00.4 as 4 milliseconds rather
  than 400 milliseconds

- ISODateTimeFormat basic field parsing too lenient
  The basic parsers in ISODateTimeFormat were too lenient
  They have been changed to only accept the correct number of digits as
  per the ISO-8601 standard. The non basic parsers are unaffected

- DateTimeFormat.forFields(List) method can't handle immutable [1877843]
  Fix so that the method does not throw an exception when an unmodifiable
  list is passed in

- Fixed offset time zones calculated incorrect periods
  ZonedChronology.ZonedDuration.isPrecise() did not take into account
  the decorated isPrecise() value. This meant that date fields for fixed
  offset time zones were always considered precise. The result was periods
  containing months and years when they should not have done.

- ZonedChronology (regression from 1.4) [1887104]
  Fix to roundFloor/roundCeiling
  Bug affected DST cutover in Autumn for time fields (not date fields)
  
- Clarify Javadoc time zone formats
  Time zone formats were incorrectly documented as 'Z' instead of 'ZZ'
  Javadoc only change

- Period formatting [2025928]
  Formatting option printZeroRarelyFirst() did not work unless years
  field was included.

- DateTimeZone (regression from 1.4) [fix also available in v1.5.2]
  Fix getOffsetFromLocal DST gap adjustment
  Bug affected parsing of DST cutover in Autumn

- Parsing (regression from 1.4) [1839440] [fix also available in v1.5.1]
  Support parsing all upper-case and all lower-case text

- Javadoc clarity enhancements [fix also available in v1.5.1]
  - Constants in Years/Months/Weeks/Days/Hours/Minutes/Seconds etc.
  - Period/Interval Object constructors
</source>
</p>
</section>

</body>
</document>
